- [Instructor] Version four of GPT is remarkable
in all that it can do today.
It has come a long way since prior versions.
Improvements include significantly better
accuracy and reasoning,
images as inputs,
and support for much larger text prompts.
However, even version four
has some clear limitations to overcome.
That said, let's recognize that
while these limitations exist today,
subsequent versions of GPT and its competitors
have a high probability of overcoming these.
In fact, this may happen sooner than many of us think.
In this video, I'll touch on a few
of the most obvious limitations of GPT-4.
Sometimes when working with GPT, the quality of the content
can make it seem that authentic thinking is happening.
That is, the software is generating creative,
original thought, and then producing the output.
GPT doesn't understand
and process prompts in the human sense.
In reality, GPT is smartly regurgitating existing data
it has been trained on,
but in a newly structured context-based form.
No doubt, it does it surprisingly well.
Alongside the best results it can produce,
the worst of humanity can also be delivered,
output that is biased, stereotypical,
wrong, offensive, explicit, nonsensical,
excessively long or way too short,
and similar are all possible.
One type of problematic output is when it is simply made up.
It's not based on any facts.
Called an AI hallucination,
GPT will sometimes produce an answer
that is simply not true.
AI doesn't have what we call common sense.
You can quickly see how that can present an issue.
An added limitation is that GPT
doesn't provide a list of data
and information sources for its output.
This can create issues that include copyright challenges,
source validation, academic accuracy,
and providing references.
If that's important to you,
I suggest adding that requirement to a prompt
or asking for references as a prompt follow-up.
GPT is optimized for both the English language
and often exhibits a Western perspective.
Other languages and cultures
are not yet being fully reflected,
creating problematic sensitivity and bias issues.
These challenges are improved through training
but can also be made worse through training.
In addition, OpenAI works continuously
to put in place guardrails
to limit the possibility of inappropriate responses.
However, this may inadvertently restrict answers
and by extension create bias and censorship concerns.
OpenAI does prohibit certain uses with GPT and ChatGPT.
Their usage policy can be found at the link on the screen.
Prohibitions include illegal activities,
generation of hateful, harassing and violent content,
creation of malware or use in weapons development.
The model relies heavily on how the prompt is constructed.
For example, one prompt may result in no answer,
while a small tweak can deliver a full answer.
This means results
can sometimes be too dependent on the user
rather than the software.
GPT's inclination is towards
answering the prompt on the first try
rather than seeking clarification if it's required.
At the time of creating this course,
GPT-4 content was current to September, 2021.
As a result, no answers are provided by the system
for requests that reference anything after that date.
Obviously, this includes no existing capability
to refresh content near real time.
Additionally, in a related limitation,
model tuning is not yet permitted by the user.
For example, a scientist may want the model
to support a niche medical area
that is not part of GPT corpus.
I can't imagine these limitations being around too long.
In this video, I've largely focused on technical issues.
It's my view that we'll overcome many of these and others
that may emerge in the months and years ahead.
Of course, it's vital to understand these limitations
as you consider the application of GPT
in your work and organization.
That said, in addition to these issues,
there are many non-technical challenges and risks
that we will also need to understand and overcome.
I discuss those in the next video.