- [Presenter] With artificial intelligence
suddenly getting so much attention
and having such a big impact across industries,
it's worth understanding how it came about.
Is AI something completely new
or has it existed for years or even decades?
Let's start with the definition.
I like this one from Merriam-Webster Dictionary:
AI is the capability of a machine
to imitate intelligent human behavior.
Most other definitions are a variation of this.
The idea that human activities can be simulated by a machine
is the core of AI research and development.
What may be a surprise to many
is that AI has been an area of interest
and progress since the 1950s,
but another way, scientists, engineers, mathematicians,
and others have been working on it for almost 70 years.
Early uses of AI included basic assembly line robotics,
chatbots, decision support tools,
and expert systems for problem solving.
In recent years,
improved computing performance and networks,
software languages and operating systems,
algorithms and big data have all contributed
to an acceleration in AI capability.
Popular culture would have us imagine AI
in the form of sentient entities
such as C-3PO in "Star Wars"
or HAL 9000 in "2001: A Space Odyssey."
In reality, AI is software that is often found
in enterprise applications and embedded in devices
from our smartphones to dishwashers,
okay, and the occasional human-looking robot.
While AI, at some level, can appear magical,
what we're actually experiencing is software
that performs a particular set of tasks well.
Given that today's common AI uses are specialized
and not general purpose just yet,
it's appropriately described as narrow AI.
While we say AI, what we're really describing
is artificial narrow intelligence or ANI.
Narrow AI differs from other forms of AI research
such as artificial general intelligence, AGI,
or artificial super intelligence, ASI,
which are in the category of strong intelligence.
This category focuses on the ability for a computer
to perform tasks through reasoning and thinking,
emulating and surpassing the intelligence of humans.
Ultimately, the software may have emotion
and self-awareness,
although don't expect any announcements on that
for some time to come.
Today's narrow AI takes existing data, the more the better,
and uses statistical techniques to help it learn
how to become progressively better at a specific task.
This approach is called machine learning or ML.
It's great at performing activities
such as returning results in online search,
image recognition such as identifying an object
in a digital photograph,
recognizing our voice commands made to Siri and Alexa,
and enabling self-driving cars to avoid collisions.
A subset of ML called deep learning
or DL uses advanced algorithms
and lots of data to support the concept
of learning by example.
For example, show a deep learning program
many pictures of bicycles
and it will soon predict with good accuracy
whether a bicycle is in a picture presented to it.
Today, AI research and applications are expanding
to include areas such as problem solving,
natural language processing and generation, NLP and NLG,
perception, planning, and robotics.
Despite how remarkable AI appears today,
it's important to recognize
that we're in the relatively early stages of its potential.
In the months and years ahead,
and as you'll see, particularly with the emergence of GPT,
its real impact is only beginning to be felt at large.
The biggest challenges of AI in the future
may not be the technology,
but questions that evolve areas
such as ethics, philosophy, culture,
regulation, politics, and economics.
We'll touch briefly on some of these areas in later videos.
Let's now continue to tell the story of AI
as we next visit the origins of OpenAI,
the organization that built and launched GPT.