- [Host] Today, AI is being used across all industries
and has many uses including fraud detection, search,
autonomous driving, spam filtering, recommendation engines
and facial recognition.
These and others belong to a variety
of categories and types within the AI domain.
GPT belongs to an AI category called Generative AI.
Other technologies and vendors are also in this category
including those being developed
and deployed from Google, Alibaba, Meta and Nvidia.
While I may occasionally allude to these other companies
in this course, we're particularly focusing
on GPT, a product of the Open AI organization.
So what exactly is generative AI?
Simply stated, generative AI is a way
for software to create new content based
on a user providing a prompt.
For example, a prompt such as draw a picture
of a mountain covered in snow would result in the output
of a unique never before seen AI generated image.
Prompts include questions, suggestions
or narratives that are created in plain language
by a user as an input,
in response to a prompt generative AI applications
then spit out new content in the form of text, images,
audio, animation, software code, and more.
Given the recent buzz around generative AI,
it may seem that it's a completely new category of AI.
In fact, generative AI was first introduced in the 1960s,
in basic computer chatbots,
so-called conversation simulators.
Significant progress was made in the early 2010s
with the emergence of GANs
or Generative Adversarial Networks,
technology that enables the creation of images,
video, and audio that appear to be authentic.
I won't go deeper on GANs in this course
but it's an area I recommend you explore
depending on how technical you want to get.
Generative AI, like a lot of categories within AI,
also owes its success to neural networks.
In simple terms, a neural network is software designed
to learn from finding patterns in datasets.
While the first neural nets first appeared as early
as the 1950s, it wasn't until the emergence of large volumes
of data and high performance computing in the early-2000s
that content generation became practical.
Additional progress was made through the use
of neural net parallel processing
on graphical processing units or GPUs,
and advances in software including GANs,
large language models, or LLMs and transformers.
I briefly discuss LLMs and transformers in the next video.
Acknowledging that the capabilities
of generative AI are emerging rapidly,
today the most common use include image
and video creation, text generation, and audio output.
In many instances, the new content is often
indistinguishable from real things or impossible to tell,
they were not created by a person.
For example, these pictures of human faces aren't real.
These people don't actually exist.
Clearly, generative AI has a lot of us excited
by its potential to transform many aspects of how we work
and live, areas that I explore in a later video.
But it also raises many questions and implications
in the realm of socioeconomics, ethics, legality
and a whole lot more.
Before proceeding,
take a few minutes to consider how generative AI
might impact your job organization or industry.