- As each day passes, greater numbers of organizations
are adopting artificial intelligence.
They're incorporating it into their products and services,
building new solutions and reinventing existing ones.
And they're using it to run better operations.
Soon, AI in an enterprise will be as ubiquitous
and as important as connectivity and electricity.
Being successful with AI, like a lot of major
industrial scale innovation over the years
will require thoughtful and strategic moves.
It will demand some tough decisions, such as dropping
or reinventing some products and services,
taking on new revenue opportunities
and reshaping the workforce.
The AI supported enterprise will require retooling employees
and perhaps even reducing staff.
Let's take a look at a few of the early actions
that businesses may want to identify
as a plan for an AI future.
As a priority at the leadership and management level,
it's important to have a vision for AI in the organization.
It should be clear on what problems AI will solve
or new opportunities that it will present.
That vision will be translated to a strategy,
a strengths, weaknesses, opportunities and threats
or SWOT analysis, will add value here.
The risks of doing both, nothing and something
must also both be evaluated.
Developing a vision and strategy
and conducting both a SWOT analysis and risk assessment
will require acquiring knowledge
on what's currently possible, and even some predictions
and bets on where AI is headed.
Leaders should attain a good understanding of AI providers,
the solutions they are shipping
and their future product and service roadmaps.
They should also closely monitor their competitors
and deeply engage their own customers on expectations.
Management must also be prepared
to take some additional investment risks
and be open to experimenting.
Fostering a culture of innovation is essential.
Research published in the Harvard Business Review
claimed that early adopters of innovation
using digital technologies, are growing twice as fast
as those who are technologically conservative.
For many organizations, short-term plans for AI
are going to be primarily focused
on acquiring or upgrading existing tools with integrated AI.
Applications that are delivered via software as a service
or SaaS, will simply see the capability
as it's made available.
In the medium term, companies will acquire new,
AI centric tools for all manner of augmentation
and automation capability, including forecasting, design,
customer service, content generation, and more.
This will be a time for developing an organization's
AI standards and principles.
In the long term, AI will necessitate many organizations
to completely reinvent themselves in order to survive.
Leadership and staff training
in a rapidly changing world of digital transformation
is more important than ever.
With AI, a training must be a high priority.
Knowing how to tap into these new AI functions
and leverage their value will enhance employee performance.
For a growing number of businesses,
there will be enthusiasm to build their own
AI powered solutions.
It's a more complex and riskier route,
but with plenty of upside,
including attaining competitive advantage.
Depending on an organization's complexity
and degree of engagement with AI systems,
it will need to consider retooling and hiring talent.
Roles will include those with AI skills and experience
such as project managers, analysts,
programmers in a variety of languages, architects,
data scientists, and perhaps even in prompt engineering.
The ability to construct high quality GPT inputs.
Preparing your organization for the challenges
and opportunities of the 21st century
means being in a forward-leaning position.
It will require bolder choices, greater risks,
in certain investments, and a culture of innovation.
And the bottom line, it'll all be for nothing
if you don't have the right skills available.