- [Instructor] I've been involved
in technology innovation for over 30 years.
During this time, I've noticed that what may be a challenge
or risk one day may not be the next.
At the same time,
new unanticipated issues often arise that nobody saw coming.
The status quo can evolve rapidly.
I guess this is characteristic of all progress
but it's particularly notable
when it comes to matters related to technology.
AI has these qualities to a significant degree.
The playing field is changing quickly
and that's why following advancements closely
is so important for you in your organization.
In areas such as strategy creation, policy development,
investment decisions, and risk management.
The range of challenges and risks
posed by AI right now are varied.
They span across economics, to ethics, and beyond.
While an organization must be focused
on the technical aspects of AI,
such as incorporating it appropriately
into their existing processes and products,
they must also be aware of the non-technical issues.
Frankly, I'm of the opinion
that the latter will be harder than the former.
Of particular concern to companies
is the impact of AI on their relevance.
If AI can deliver a solution in an automated way that is,
for example, cheaper, faster, and a better experience,
it will displace existing providers
who don't pivot quickly enough.
Automation has always presented this risk
but AI-powered automation,
which can have greater generalization,
will often happen and be far reaching
much faster than in the past.
This issue applies to skills to.
A once important skill now, done better with AI,
means employees need to retool quickly.
OpenAI's research indicates that GPT, for instance,
may impact 10% of the work tasks
of 80% of the U.S. workforce.
For sure, there's also an upside
to the opportunities for work that AI presents,
and I discuss those in a later video.
Even as companies recognize the need to change,
they may also be limited by technical know-how,
innovation capabilities, and insufficient urgency
from all decision makers.
Necessary change won't happen
if leaders and staff don't understand AI,
fail to embrace it, and even reject it.
A poorly executed AI strategy
could result in a business making bad decisions.
Those informed by ChatGPT, for example,
or using poor data to train its language models,
running a foul of regulations and laws,
and damaging its brands through unethical AI behaviors.
After all, AI continues to reflect human biases
and it produces AI hallucinations.
AI now has the ability to create outputs,
such as fake images, video,
and audio that is difficult to distinguish from reality.
Deep fakes, for example, are videos that show
what appears to be a real person discussing a subject
but that has been entirely generated by a computer.
On one level, this can be entertaining
but it does raise the question of how we will distinguish
between what is real and what is fake in the near future.
What happens, for example, if a supposed video of your CEO
appears on YouTube appearing drunk, cursing,
and being inappropriate?
Sure, eventually the truth will likely emerge,
but until then, the stock could tank
and the reputation of the business may never fully recover.
Using fake content, AI will enable all types
of nefarious schemes to take place,
including those impacting our political systems
elaborate cyber crimes
and ultimately creating significant issues of trust
in all aspects of life.
Can you imagine getting a call from someone
and not being sure if the person on the other end is real?
We can anticipate an entirely new industry emerging
to combat these challenges.
The ethics of AI, a topic beyond the scope of this course,
yet relevant to challenges and risks
are still not well understood or implemented.
Here we're talking about people, organizations,
and systems and how their use of AI, for example,
demonstrates transparency,
such as whether content is copyrighted,
shows fairness in its interactions, respects privacy,
and provides an explanation
of how decisions and actions are being processed.
In the absence of a formal approach to ethical AI use,
people and organizations
will certainly raise their risk quotient.
Finally, significant work is required
to reduce the challenges of the AI alignment problem.
Simply defined, this is the issue
of ensuring AI response to human requests,
such that they remain within moral,
ethical, and legal standards.
For example, if we asked a self-driving car
to pick up and deliver medicine from a drugstore
as quickly as possible,
would it knock over people and crash into objects
all in an effort to optimize for speed?
We want AI to augment
and improve our lives and organizations,
but we don't want it to create chaos we can't control.
You can probably get the sense
that I'm only scratching the surface here.
There's much more to learn
and I strongly encourage you
to dive deeper into these topics.
Before continuing to the next video,
consider what you believe to be the greatest limitations,
challenges, and risks of GPT.