- To understand what motivated the formation of OpenAI,
the San Francisco based company behind GPT,
requires a brief discussion on an ongoing core debate
within the AI community.
This debate asks whether advances in AI present,
on one side of the argument,
a better, more prosperous future,
or on the other side, a future where AI is to be feared.
Those who say AI is a positive force,
such as Ray Kurzweil, the American inventor and futurist,
argues that it will free up humans for more leisure time
and enable more of us to focus on creative pursuits.
Those on the other concerned side of the argument,
such as Bill Gates, the former CEO of Microsoft,
worry that AI, while remarkable, may be dangerous.
He fears, for example, AI being applied in warfare
to manage autonomous weapons, those that search for
and destroy targets without human intervention.
Elon Musk, the CEO of Tesla, SpaceX, and Twitter,
has been outspoken about his concerns.
He shares views similar to the late Stephen Hawking,
the notable theoretical physicist and cosmologist.
They have characterized some form of future AI
as potentially humanity's "greatest existential threat,"
a concerning view indeed.
Responding to this concern, in October, 2015,
Elon Musk along with Sam Altman,
former president of startup accelerator Y Combinator,
and other investors
such as co-founder of LinkedIn Reid Hoffman
and Peter Thiel, co-founder of PayPal, created OpenAI.
Corporations such as Microsoft, who recently,
significantly increased its investment in OpenAI,
and Infosys were also founding members.
Acknowledging their concerns about the risks of future AI,
they committed to actions that could prevent major risks.
These partners formed OpenAI in the spirit of promoting
and developing AI in a manner that would benefit humanity.
To demonstrate their commitment,
together they pledged over $1 billion
to create the organization.
Their mission was clear.
OpenAI would be focused on ensuring that the development
and usage of Artficial General Intelligence,
or AGI, would benefit the world.
They would build safe AGI
and consider their mission successful
if it helped others achieve the same outcome.
The organization began as a nonprofit
in early 2016 with nine researchers.
By April of that year,
they released their first product called OpenAI Gym.
This was a toolkit for developing
and comparing reinforcement learning algorithms.
Reinforcement learning is when a computer employs trial
and error to come up with a solution to a problem.
In December, 2016, OpenAI released Universe.
This was a platform for enabling AI software
to interact with a computer,
such as viewing what's on the screen
and using a virtual keyboard and mouse.
These solutions were followed by several more
in the machine learning space.
In 2018, OpenAI published a paper on Generative Pre-Training
and what would soon become the first version
of GPT software.
At first, much of the code behind OpenAI was open source,
thus the use of the term "Open" in its name,
enabling others to inspect, modify,
and distribute the code for their purposes.
Transparency and sharing were consistent
with the organization's founding mission.
However, as with so many initial intentions,
strategy can often change in response to market conditions,
leadership, philosophy, and opportunity.
In 2019, OpenAI dropped its designation as a pure nonprofit
and became a for-profit enterprise.
This was done for a variety of reasons
that included the ability to attract further investment
through monetization opportunities.
Microsoft stepped forward and became a significant investor.
Further, Microsoft became OpenAI's preferred partner
to license its technology and integrate it
into their existing and future products and services.
In addition, Elon Musk resigned from his board seat.
He cited a potential conflict of interest
with the work at Tesla in developing AI
for self-driving cars, as well as his concerns
about the new for-profit direction.
With the massive success of ChatGPT and GPT-4,
OpenAI is pushing the boundaries of what is possible.
It's becoming clear already
that OpenAI's competition will be rigorous
and the future incredibly unpredictable for all of us.