- [Instructor] The Open AI organization is notable
not just by their track record
in releasing groundbreaking AI solutions,
but by its published mission
to support the use of artificial general intelligence,
AGI for the benefit of all humanity.
Note, though that AGI is aspirational
and doesn't yet exist.
That said, it's clearly the pursuit of many
and the AI capabilities we are experiencing today
are likely points along the way.
The subject of how we humanely approach AI
is not novel to OpenAI.
The ethical use of AI,
now often refer to as responsible AI is concerned
with ensuring the development and use of AI
with positive intentions and fairness
to all that it impacts.
It's about considering safety, security,
care and accountability in AI creation and use.
Stakeholders include business leaders,
university researchers, and governments.
For example, the topic of AI regulation and legislation
is firmly part of global discourse.
In the United Arab Emirates, for instance,
there's a minister of AI
whose purview includes the ethics of AI.
How to move forward responsibly with AI is a topic
being discussed in government buildings across the world.
AI ethics include areas such as bias,
weaponization, morality,
robot autonomy, and liability.
Each of these are beyond the scope of this course
but depending on your interest may warrant further research,
including delving into the related AI courses
in the LinkedIn Learning library.
Now, let's turn our attention back to OpenAI.
In 2019, in an attempt to capture the principles
by which they execute their mission
of supporting the development and deployment of AGI
for the benefit of humanity, OpenAI published a charter.
The document found on their website is a codified expression
of their strategy
and was developed with feedback from inside
and outside the organization.
It's an important artifact
that goes beyond communicating their values.
It can provide inspiration and guidance to others
who are looking to adopt similar approaches.
While I encourage everyone to read the charter
and I include a link on the screen,
here is a brief overview of the main four principles.
First, the benefits of AGI should be enjoyed by everyone.
The focus should remain on the advantages
to all of humanity.
Second, AGI Research and development should be safe.
In addition and particularly notable,
if an AGI project emerges from a competitor
that could incentivize speed to market
at the cost of safety, OpenAI will not compete
and will instead partner and assist the competitor.
Third, OpenAI will strive
to demonstrate technical leadership
in order to amplify the benefits of AI and AGI.
Finally, they're committed to broad collaboration
with research and policy institutions across the world.
Central to this is
sharing as much of their research as is reasonable.
They want to participate in the building
of a strong AGI community across the planet
to ensure that AGI challenges are addressed.
I'm sure you'll agree that these are admirable
and lofty principles.
However, the degree to which they can be met
over the long term and whether OpenAI will adhere to them
are unknown at this time.
We'll let others discuss and debate that.
Perhaps the charter's most enduring quality
is that it can inspire others to create a positive roadmap
for their AI efforts.
After all, with the stakes being so high,
we should be motivated
to reduce the potential risks inherent to a world
driven by AI.
Now, before proceeding to the next video,
as a suggestion, pause for a few moments to consider
and write down what principles you think would be important
for your organization in its pursuit of AI.