- For thousands of years, humans have been using all manner
of complex tools to assist in their daily activities.
It's what separates us
from most of the rest of the animal kingdom.
Augmenting our work has largely been welcomed.
Over time our tools have become
vastly more elaborate and helpful.
Without machines, for example,
the Industrial Revolutions would've been impossible,
and the world we know today would not exist.
Directly and indirectly, advancements in these tools
and machines have resulted in the elevation
of billions of people out of extreme poverty.
Today, with a combination
of robotics and artificial intelligence, or AI,
smart machines are designing, developing,
and deploying solutions with much less input from humans.
AI-enabled capabilities powered by game-changing software
and vast amounts of data are demonstrating familiar
and convincing human behaviors, such as making things,
problem-solving, and pattern recognition.
There are few places where AI is more apparent today
than in our factories and offices.
Enterprise applications are increasingly being powered
by AI-enabled software.
We see use of this software in areas such as cybersecurity,
financial forecasting, engineering, coding, design,
and in product lifecycle and supply chain management.
New AI capabilities are being introduced all the time.
However, sometimes there is a sudden leap in innovation.
In 2018, one such event happened.
GPT version one was released.
GPT, or Generative Pre-trained Transformer,
was created by OpenAI,
a San Francisco based research laboratory.
GPT, and specifically its solution called ChatGPT,
released in November 2022,
would introduce the existing concept
of generative AI to the broader world.
This is software that takes input provided
by a person or machine and creates remarkable output
in the form of text, audio, and visuals.
Since its release in 2018,
several new versions of GPT have been introduced,
expanding and improving what it can deliver.
Today, there is a scramble to embed GPT
and related generative AI capabilities
into all types of existing solutions
and to create completely new solutions.
This course covers GPT in general,
but with version four as the basis
for the capabilities explored and examples provided.
Before I jump deep into GPT, let's first step back
and briefly understand the AI journey
that has taken us to where we are today.