- [Presenter] In November, 2022,
in what we may look back as a pivotal moment in history,
OpenAI released ChatGPT and made it available for free
to anyone who signed up.
Overnight, millions could use this generative AI tool,
a type of sophisticated chatbot, to get detailed answers
to questions and generate new content.
Up until this point, OpenAI products
including prior versions of GPT were only accessible
to certain users such as developers and academics,
and often, for a fee.
By releasing ChatGPT for everyone at no cost,
for the first time, high-end AI became broadly accessible.
In fact, within two months of its public launch,
ChatGPT had 100 million users, breaking the world record
to become the fastest-growing web application ever.
By simply entering a plain language prompt,
users discovered they could quickly have ChatGPT,
for example, create essays, write software code,
develop resumes, compose emails,
and summarize content.
This was generative AI at work.
For the free version, OpenAI based ChatGPT
on version 3.5 of GPT.
While the public gets all the benefits
from having free access, OpenAI is motivated by the upside
of having millions of people participate in GPT research
as well as the feedback process.
A premium version of ChatGPT called ChatGPT Plus
was released in early 2023
and uses the more sophisticated GPT-4 version.
In addition to being more accurate
and capable than the free version,
ChatGPT Plus also has faster response times,
better capacity management,
and provides earlier access to new features.
What may surprise many is that leaps in the quality
of output in recent versions of GPT and ChatGPT
are being helped as a result of human trainers.
Called Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback, or RLHF,
GPT is provided with feedback by a person
on generated output, and this feedback is then incorporated
back into the large language model.
This cycle of output and feedback
rapidly improves the model.
At the heart of ChatGPT are input prompts.
The quality of output is a direct result
of well-constructed prompts.
Crafting prompts is referred to as prompt engineering.
It wouldn't be my first choice for a term
that easily rolls off the tongue, but nevertheless,
it appears to have stuck.
Remember, a prompt isn't simply a question similar
to what we've become accustomed to with search engines.
Of course, ChatGPT handles questions well,
providing one answer rather than links
to thousands of possible results.
It has far more elaborate capabilities
that include sorting and classifying information,
creating software code and generating,
rewriting, summarizing, and expanding text.
To get the most from ChatGPT, it requires both a period
of experimentation and also good technique.
It's okay, for instance, to keep rewriting your request
until you get an output closer to what you want.
Each time a response is given by ChatGPT, it's different.
Also, given that ChatGPT retains awareness
of everything captured in a single conversation session
means it will use those insights
to inform its output for you.
For now though, once you close the window or app,
that memory is lost.
When crafting a prompt, you can use commands
to begin your sentence, such as write,
summarize, translate, and create.
Add context to your request.
For example, you could prompt,
"What are good gym exercises for a 30-minute workout?"
However, you might add prior to that,
"I want to build muscle in my arms."
Then follow it with your questions.
It works well, too, to add identity.
For example, in the gym example,
you might add, "Provide the exercises
for a male between the ages of 30 and 40."
This works for all manner of prompts.
You could ask ChatGPT to write an email
that comes from a boss to an employee
or from an employee to a boss.
ChatGPT loves specificity and descriptions.
It also benefits from providing examples in the prompt.
For instance, "I enjoy The Beatles
and The Rolling Stones.
Suggest bands with similar styles."
You'll find a lot of help creating prompts online.
Here are three sites to give you a flavor
of what's available.
Here's PromptBase.
This is a solution that provides a database
of effective prompts that gets results
in a wide number of generative AI tools,
such as Midjourney and Stable Diffusion.
Next, Vellum.
This is a site, which is a suite of tools
in support of LLMs.
It includes features that help with prompt engineering.
Finally, FusionAI is a support tool
that will generate prompts
based on what you're trying to achieve.
It will iterate with you until you get the desired output.
ChatGPT is impressive and powerful,
but it's certainly not perfect.
It's still early in its development.
You'll find that it sometimes can't answer your prompt
including having no knowledge after September, 2021
because that data is not included
in its large language model.
I suspect that this limitation will disappear soon though.
ChatGPT may also give an answer it simply makes up.
We call this an AI hallucination.
Open AI's use policy also prohibits certain uses.
While ChatGPT is one app that runs in GPT,
there are many more.
Next, we'll explore some of those other applications of GPT.