- While the important debate
over the potential negative impacts
of AI on existing jobs continues,
let's also recognize
that in every technological and societal shift,
there are also plenty of winners.
Each of the previous industrial revolutions
made many jobs and businesses obsolete,
but they also generated completely new work and industries
that more often generated better economics
than those they replaced.
Sure, AI is anticipated to eliminate a lot of work,
but it's important that we don't lose sight of the fact
that new lucrative AI careers and business opportunities
will also emerge in the years ahead.
Any discussion on the future of AI
must include the jobs and careers it will create
and the ways it will augment the way many work.
By transforming what and how work is delivered,
according to the consulting firm, McKinsey,
AI is projected to contribute $13 trillion
to the global economy by 2030.
The World Economic Forum is on record
predicting that AI will create 97 million new jobs by 2025.
Looking just at generative AI, the realm of GPT,
a Goldman Sachs study suggests it could produce
a $7 trillion increase in global GDP by the early 2030s.
These numbers, of course, can vary
depending on how we define the scope of AI.
Should we include robots in our definition, for example?
Broadly though, much of the value
that AI will bring over the next few years
can be distilled into three major buckets:
improved customer experiences,
new revenue opportunities, and cost reductions.
Consider for a moment
a few of the different types of new AI-centric businesses
and jobs that may be created to support these areas.
Equally important too is to evaluate
what roles these efforts might displace.
Today, most organizations recognize the role of technology,
and particularly digitalization as a core mechanism
for achieving these strategic objectives.
The ongoing digital transformation of the global economy
will continue to drive demand in technology-related jobs.
AI-specific work may require more technical education
and specialization.
The need for data-focused jobs,
given the intersection between AI and digitalization,
will also continue to increase.
According to CompTIA, a leading technology association,
the top five AI skills for IT professionals
include support and troubleshooting of AI issues,
AI algorithm development,
software development in general,
cybersecurity, and data analysis.
And what about generative AI?
This area is creating a demand for roles
that include prompt engineers,
the role that specializes in creating the best input
for a GPT.
All types of data-related roles,
AI product owners, AI trainers.
These are for training AI, not people.
Lots of backend technical engineering roles,
science and research work, and analysts.
What will surprise us all in the future
will be the essential roles
that we can't even imagine right now.
In an environment of work disruption
and future career uncertainty,
at least in the short to medium term,
if you're thoughtful and strategic
about your skills development,
there will be opportunities.
If you're inclined towards a role in the world of AI,
demand will be high for some time to come,
and completely new work will emerge.
Stay informed, be proactive, and remain optimistic.