- GPT stands for generative pre-trained transformer.
A name like that was obviously created
by people that know nothing about marketing.
It's certainly a mouthful.
The joking aside, GPT uses complex algorithms,
a set of rules for problem-solving
that computers follow,
and lots of data to generate original text
and other media types.
The quality of text output that Version 4
of GPT produces is high quality and hard to discern
from human-generated text.
With some prompting from a user,
GPT can create, for example, meaningful stories,
poems, emails, chatbot responses, and software code.
In addition, unlike previous versions
of GPT, Version 4 is multimodal
in that it also supports visual inputs, not just text.
GPT is based on a generative model of language.
Generative models use existing knowledge
of language to make predictions
on what words may come next based
on a series of previous words and contexts.
This is where we get the word generative,
the G in GPT.
As a simple example, if you type, "Once upon a,"
the model will predict the word time
as the next word based on its analysis of a large corpus
of data that is managed via a large language model, or LLM.
The LLM, which is a complex algorithm,
not the data itself, but AI relevant parameters, is derived
from a massive volume of data that's trained on.
This data comes from a variety of public sources
including Wikipedia and Common Crawl, a data set of billions
of web pages.
To help train to make the system smart,
so to speak,
text is randomly removed from the acquired content
and the software is trained to fill it
in with the correct missing words.
This is where we get the word pre-trained,
or P, in GPT.
Powering all of this is a type of AI called deep learning,
which is based on 70 years of research in neural networks.
As an example, for an AI-powered recognition system
to learn what a bicycle is and identified in a picture,
AI must analyze large volumes of existing bicycle pictures.
It's called a neural network because it loosely
mimics the function of the brain.
The network consists of a web of connected nodes
or data points.
The type of neural network used in GPT
is called a transformer.
That's the T in GPT.
It's particularly good
at taking text and reusing it in another context
or word sequence,
while maintaining meaning.
In a neural network,
data moves through nodes, data points,
based on certain criteria.
One of these criteria is the weight
or strength of connections between nodes.
If criteria are not met, data does not get processed.
If it does, it moves to another node.
This repeats until the data arrives transformed
at the end of the neural network.
Large language models, or LMMs,
are at the heart
of the artificial intelligence in generative AI.
These LLMs contain parameters,
which I'll explain in a moment.
Basically, more parameters mean higher accuracy output.
In each subsequent version of GPT
the number of parameters has increased massively.
Version 1 had around 117 million.
Version 2 had 1.5 billion,
and Version 3 had 175 billion.
OpenAI has not revealed the exact number
of parameters in version four, but some analysts estimate it
at over a trillion.
Even as an estimate,
that may be a few billion off, that's some leap.
And you can see now where GPT4 gets its smarts.
So what are these parameters in a large language model?
There are values that have been derived
from analyzing lots of data.
Think of a set
of parameters like the temperature, direction, and speed
of air from vents that you control in your car.
You can adjust these until you get just the right mix
of air that makes you feel comfortable.
In the case of GPT, the response you get
to an input prompt will be the result of a series
of parameters chosen along a neural network that correspond
to text or other output.
It is the prediction that the right set
of parameters will provide the correct output.
Okay, I'll stop there.
The concepts described here provide the basic foundation
of what GPT is and how it works.
It will be enough for most people, but there's a lot more
under the hood if you decide you want to go deeper.