- [Instructor] The central function of GPT
is the ability to ingest large amounts of data
and use it as a basis to create original output
in the form of text, video, and audio.
The quality of text output, for example,
is so high that it's often difficult to distinguish it
from something written by a person.
To enable and support this high quality output,
a number of AI techniques are employed
to make sense of input provided.
GPT utilizes an approach
that is at the intersection of computer and data science
and human language
called natural language processing or NLP.
Let's begin with an example of NLP in action.
Many of us now issue voice commands to digital services
such as the popular virtual assistants
Amazon Alexa and Google Home.
These devices listen to our words, process this input,
and then execute some actions
such as playing a favorite album or turning on a light.
This same technology that makes sense of voice commands
can also be applied to text input on a computer.
This enables solutions such as chatbots,
search engines, language translation, and spell check.
In all these instances
AI is tasked with processing language, either audio or text.
At a high level, NLP generally works like this.
The software needs to pre-process the text in sentences
in order to provide some form of structure
that can be used as the basis for interpretation.
First, the sentence is broken into each word.
This is called tokenization.
The individual words are known as tokens.
Unnecessary punctuation is removed.
Next words could be identified
and tagged as nouns, verbs, adjectives, pronouns, et cetera.
This is followed by the process of stemming.
This is where words are standardized
and put in context by reducing them to their root form.
For example, the words banks, banker, and banking
are all associated with the root word bank.
This is a stem.
That root word will be used to assign the context
for the input to, for example, a financial institution
and not the act of turning an aircraft.
Once the text has been pre-processed,
a machine learning or ML algorithm
is used to interpret the input text.
These algorithms use statistical models
based on vast volumes of data called training data
to suggest what action to perform.
These statistical models are also referred to as
large language models or LLMs.
When the pre-processed text is analyzed by the ML algorithm,
it is looking for words, phrases, and patterns
of text that are familiar from the training data.
If there is a high probability
that the words and context are understood,
the software now knows what to do next.
In my examples, NLP is being used to take an action
such as retrieving a search result
or changing the temperature on a thermostat.
However, input could also be used to generate
new media outputs, such as text, audio, and video.
This is where we get the term generative AI
and it's where we'll go in the next video.