- Not withstanding some limitations.
If you've used ChatGPT recently,
it doesn't fail to impress.
Similarly, as more applications integrate GPT capabilities,
the results are often remarkable.
For example, a solution such as room GPT
takes input of a photo of a room and almost instantly
produces output of the room redesigned.
What used to take interior designers years
of training and hours
of time to produce is now created in seconds.
In just months, thousands
of new solutions have emerged that automate
and reinvent how we do all matter of things.
Every day more emerge, placing a heavy burden
on the status quo.
If this is the impact and response we're experiencing now,
what will the world of AI look like
in just 18 or 24 months from now?
It's both an exhilarating and daunting thought.
While we can expect more groundbreaking innovation
that will be useful, embraced by many,
we'll also see more tension being paid
to areas such as regulation
and perhaps some form of global collaboration
to manage risks to economies, society, and humanity overall.
It's going to be a tumultuous time.
There are many aspects to consider on a continuum.
On one end, part of society believes AI is fairly benign
and will positively support humans much as technology has
in the past.
While on the other extreme end, people believe
AI presents an existential threat to humanity.
I think you'll agree there's a big range between
these two perspectives and what they mean for the future.
It's a safe bet to assume that both the capabilities,
challenges, and responses to AI will heat up
in the months ahead, each serving up generous amounts
of uncertainty.
For you and I and the organizations we work with,
it's a time for education, experimentation, investment,
and risk management.
There's an enormous amount of value that AI is bringing
to augment all types of work.
No matter the industry, AI will have an impact.
For example, we should see accelerated progress
in areas such as medicine, agriculture, sustainability,
and autonomous transportation.
Keep closely apprised on such developments relevant
to your industry.
I created this short video course to introduce the basics
of AI and GPT.
It's just the start.
For next steps, I recommend checking out
my highly popular Foundations
of the Fourth Industrial Revolution course.
This will help to put AI and other trends
into a broader perspective for you.
Next, you could check out many of the wonderful AI courses
on LinkedIn learning by other authors.
They cover just about every aspect of the topic
from prompt engineering to coding.
Now, as we come to the end, let me ask you a question.
Is it possible that some part
of this video course was written by GPT?
And more importantly,
would it make a difference if you knew?
With that, I wish you continued success with your goals.
Thank you for watching and good luck.