- Artificial intelligence is now creating
compelling text and visual content.
This content is of such high quality,
it's hard to differentiate it from that created by a person.
Called generative AI, it's enabling
remarkable new capabilities
for individuals and organizations.
Hi, I'm Dr. Jonathan Reichental,
business owner, professor, and author.
Let me take you on a brief journey
to introduce the basics of AI
and a version of generative AI called GPT.
Now is the time to understand the opportunities,
limitations, and risks presented by this new technology.
This course will provide you with a solid foundation
and I'm confident it will inspire you to learn more.
Okay, let's do this.